A Guide to the Barbara Abernathy papers, 1986-2005
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library
Barbara Abernathy papers, 1986-2005
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library
M 362
1.4 linear feet.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Barbara Abernathy, April 13, 2006.
Biographical Information
Barbara Abernathy is a longtime community advocate for the Carver neighborhood of Richmond, Virginia. Abernathy spent her childhood in Carver and graduated from Maggie Walker High School. After graduating, she left the Richmond area for several years to pursue opportunities in Washington, D.C. and Massachusetts, and she returned to Carver in 1977. Soon after, Abernathy began her involvement with community advocacy, first joining the West of Belvidere Civic Association, and later, the Carver Area Civic Improvement League (CACIL). In the early 1990s, Abernathy was elected president of CACIL, a position she held for fourteen years until she stepped down in January 2007. In 1996, Abernathy reached out to Virginia Commonwealth University's (VCU) president, Dr. Eugene Trani, and the two formed an agreement which established the Carver-VCU Partnership. The goal of the partnership is to "create a shared urban community with a commitment to improving the neighborhood's quality of life, while providing learning opportunities for students." Abernathy served as co-chair of the partnership for eleven years. Abernathy has also served on committees and boards for numerous Richmond organizations including the Richmond Planning Commission, the Mayor's Commission on Trees, the Census 2000 Task Force, the Pride in Richmond Recreation and Parks Advisory Board, the Better Housing Coalition, and Virginia Supportive Housing. In 1998 she was named the Richmond Redevelopment and Housing Authority volunteer of the year, and in 2004, she received the Virginia Housing Coalition Award for community development.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of records created or acquired by Abernathy in the course of her work as a community advocate. Materials relating to Richmond Redevelopment and Housing Authority Housing Authority, Neighborhoods in Bloom, and the Carver-VCU Partnership make up the bulk of the collection. The collection also includes Carver Area Civic Improvement League (CACIL) minutes, by-laws, membership applications, and meeting attendance records. Abernathy's personal files consist of her notes on CACIL meetings and drafts of speeches she has given. The majority of the correspondence consists of letters from Abernathy to Carver residents and city officials. Most of the letters addressed to Abernathy concern the Carver-VCU Partnership. The collection also includes newspaper clippings, photographic materials, drawings, and other publications.
Arrangement
The collection is divided into eight series: Series 1: Personal Files, 1997-1998; Series 2: Correspondence, 1987-2003; Series 3: Carver Area Civic Impovement League, 1988-2003; Series 4: Richmond City Government Files, 1987-2005; Series 5: Carver-VCU Partnership, 1996-2001; Series 6: Historic Place Registration, 1998; Series 7: Clippings, 1986-2005; and Series 8: Other Publications, 1987-2002.
Files are arranged alphabetically by subject, thereunder chronologically.
Contents List
- Series 1: Personal Files, 1997-1998
  - Notes, 1997-1998, undated (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Speeches, undated (Box-folder 1:2)
- Series 2: Correspondence, 1987-2003
  - Correspondence, 1987-1997 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Correspondence, 1998-2003, undated (Box-folder 1:4)
- Series 3: Carver Area Civic Improvement League, 1988-2003
  - CACIL Minutes, 1988-2003 (Box-folder 1:5)
  - CACIL Bylaws, 1988, 2002 (Box-folder 1:6)
  - CACIL Membership Files, 1989-1995, 2001-2003 (Box-folder 1:7)
  - CACIL Miscellaneous, 1997-2003 (Box-folder 1:8)
- Series 4: Richmond City Government Files, 1987-2005
  - Richmond Redevelopment and Housing Authority, 1987-1999, undated (Box-folder 1:9)
  - Richmond Redevelopment and Housing Authority, February 2000 (Box-folder 1:10)
  - Richmond Redevelopment and Housing Authority, March 2000-2005 (Box-folder 1:11)
  - Neighborhoods in Bloom, 1999-2003, undated (Box-folder 1:12)
  - Photos and Drawings, undated (Box-folder 1:13)
- Series 5: Carver-VCU Partnership, 1996-2001
  - Carver-VCU Partnership, 1996-2001, undated (Box-folder 1:14)
- Series 6: Historic Place Registration, 1998
  - Historic Place Registration, 1998, undated (Box-folder 1:15)
- Series 7: Clippings 1986-2005
  - Clippings, 1986-2005, undated (Box-folder 1:16)
- Series 8: Other Publications, 1987-2002
  - Other Publications, 1987-2002, undated (Box-folder 1:17)